Finding Aid for Roger Irving Wykes papers, 1889 and 1907-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Roger Irving Wykes papers 1889 and 1907-1938
Wykes, Roger Irving, 1874-
3 linear feet
86385 Aa 2
Attorney General of Michigan, 1912. Briefs and other legal papers relating to the Duluth, South Shore and Atlantic Railroad case and the Grand Rapids Gas Company case; correspondence, 1907-1908, on his campaign and activities in the Michigan Constitutional Convention; scrapbooks on the Constitutional Convention and Michigan politics, 1907-1920.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Frederic K. Wykes (donor no. 3446 ) and came to the library in 1958.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Roger I. Wykes was born in Grand Rapids on September 6, 1874, and educated in the Grand Rapids and South Grand Rapids High Schools. He then taught school for two years before entering the Law School of the University of Michigan. He graduated in 1895, then in 1896 began the practice of law in Grand Rapids.
Over the course of his career, Wykes became a specialist in laws affecting railroads. From 1897 to 1904 he was with the Michigan Attorney General's office, in charge of litigation against railroads and other corporations regarding their compliance with state laws regulating rates and tax liability. From 1904 to 1906, he was assistant general counsel of the Grand Rapids & Indiana Railway Company.
In May, 1907, he was elected a delegate to the state's Constitutional Convention, where he served on the Committee on Finance and Taxation. From 1910 to 1911, Wykes was a member of the Grand Rapids Charter Commission. In 1912, he was a member and president of the Special Committee of Inquiry into Taxation Methods in the State of Michigan. That same year, he was appointed to fill out the un-expired term of the state's Attorney General. From 1915 to 1917, he was general counsel for the Association of Michigan Railways. During this same period of time, 1905-1920, Wykes was retained by the Attorney General as special counsel in railway, telegraph, telephone and express rate, tax and charter cases.
The Roger Irving Wykes papers are comprised of four series: Correspondence; Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1907-1908; Miscellaneous; and Litigation Case Files. Most of the correspondence relates to his campaign for delegate to the Constitutional Convention. The great bulk of the Litigation series relates to his participation in the Duluth South Shore and Atlantic Railroad Company Rate Case.
Subjects:
Duluth South Shore and Atlantic Railway Company.; Grand Rapids Gas Company.; Michigan. Dept. of Attorney General; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1907-1908); Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Public utilities--Michigan.; Railroads--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Wykes, Roger Irving, 1874-
Contributors:
Blair, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1854-1912.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - June 1907 (Box 1)
  - July 1907 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Arthur H. Vandenberg)
  - August 1907 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1938 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1907-1908
  - Papers, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1907-1908 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook, 1912-1920 concerning Wykes' political activities (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous family documents, autograph book, land abstract, etc. (Box 1)
  - Paper: "A Railway Rate Case; involving the power of, and limitations upon, public control and the means and procedure to, and the principles governing, relief from excesses of state authority" (Box 1)
  - Diary of Hattie Jennings of trip from Ann Arbor to Europe, 1889 (Box 1)
- Litigation Case Files
  - Grand Rapids Gas Light Company v. Michigan Trust Company (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids East Side Water Power, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Duluth South Shore and Atlantic Railroad Company Rate Case, 1913-1914
    - 1913-1914 (Box 2)
    - 1913-1914 (Box 3)